大家好
so hi everyone
很高兴回到这里，并能看到你们这么多人
I'm so great to be back here and see so many of you
是的，我想这次紧张感一直没有消失，所以我还是
and yeah I think this never get off so I'm still
很紧张，希望你们不要介意
very nervous so hope you don't mind so
是的，我希望你们喜欢这次会议
yeah and I hope you enjoyed the conference so far
像我一样
as much as I do
我们已经听了很多从技术视角
so we had a lot of great talks and discussions from
进行的精彩的演讲和讨论
technical perspective
今天我想
and today I'd like to
做一个相对非技术性的演讲
give a relative non technical talk
希望它能
and hope it can
给你们带来一些思考和启发
bring you some thoughts and inspiration
首先让我介绍一下自己，我叫Anthony Fu
so first let me introduce myself my name is Anthony Fu
嗨
and hi
我女朋友安妮斯为我画了这个可爱的头像
my girlfriend Ennes draw me this cute avatar
还有我们稍后会看到的一些卡通画
and also the electrician we're going to see later
所以谢谢她
so thanks to her
是的，我叫 Anthony Fu
and yeah so my name is Anthony Fu
我是 Nuxt、Vue 和 Vite的核心团队成员
and I'm the core team member of Nuxt
我也是 VueUse、Slidev
View and Vite I'm also the creator of VueUse, Slidev
Vitest、Unocss 等一些
Vitest, UnoCss and a few
其他的开源项目的创建者
other open source projects
目前我在 Nuxt Lab 的框架团队工作
so I'm currently working at Nuxt Lab on the framework team
你可以在我的网站上 antfu.me 找到我
so you can find me on my website antfu.me and
这里有所有你需要的链接
this should has all the links you need
我非常感谢我能有这个机会
so um I really appreciate the chance I got to
让我能够全职从事开源工作
allows me to work in open source full time
我想对所有给予我支持和机会的人说声谢谢
and I would like to say thank you for everyone
谢谢你们
that's giving
给了我支持和机会
giving me the support
让我能够实现这一切
and opportunity that make this possible to me
一直以来，我的梦想就是从事开源工作
so it'll always be my dream to work in open source
并创造一些东西
and build things
可以帮助
that can help
世界各地的人们
the people around the world
就像参加这样的精彩活动
like attending awesome events like this
并在社区中遇到许多优秀的人一样
and meeting so many great people in the community
我相信很多像我一样的人
so I believe many of you like me
都对从事开源感兴趣
are interested in doing open source
所以今天我想在这里分享一些
so today here I'd like to share
我的想法和经验
some of my thoughts and the experience I got
希望能给你们一些
and hopefully can provide you some
关于你们自己开源之路的启发
inspirations on your own open source journey
开源是一个很大的话题
so open source is a quite big topic
我不可能在一个演讲中涵盖所有内容
and I cannot really cover everything in one talk
所以我会尝试把它分解开
so I'm trying to break it down
并在每次演讲中讨论不同方面
and talk about different aspects of open source in each talk
并把它做成一个系列
and make them a series
今天讲的是第二部分
so today is going to be the part 2
渐进之路
the progressive path
之前的演讲是集合论
the previous episode is about The Set Theory
我在几个会议上已经讲过
where I already given a few conferences
而且那个主题与今天的主题独立
and the topic was independent from today's
所以如果你错过了也不要担心
so don't worry if you have missed it
如果你感兴趣的话
and in case you are interested
你可以在我的网站antfu.me上找到录音
you can find the recordings on my website antfu.me afterwrad
首先，在我们深入今天的主题之前
so first before we dive into today's topic
让我们讨论一下
let's discuss a bit
我们对开源的期望是什么
about what we are expecting from open source
我们知道大多数我们使用的开源项目
we know that most of the open source
都是实际日常用的工具
projects that we use daily are actual tools
你是否曾经考虑过这样一个问题
and have you ever thought about the question that
什么定义了工具
what defines a tool
这个定义应该非常简单
the definition should be pretty straightforward and
也许你已经有了答案
maybe you already have the answer in your mind
在我看来
and in my interpretation
工具应该帮助你更快更轻松地完成任务
a tool should help you to get things done faster and easier
至少是它的功能之一
at least one of them
我想没有人愿意使用一个让事情变得
I guess no one wants to use a tool that makes things
更慢或更复杂的工具，对吧
slower or more complicated right
所以假设我们想要建立一个新的开源项目
so assume we want to build a new open source project
一个供人们使用的工具
a tool for people to use
你会考虑什么来判断你要构建的工具
and what would you consider to justify if a tool you
是否是一个好工具
are going to build is a good one or not
我的答案是否定的
well my answer is no
你无法真正确定
you cannot really tell
除非经过社区的验证
without being verified by the community
因为有太多的因素可以影响
because there are so many factors that can affect
一个开源项目是否成功
if an open source project will work out or not
但是我也想强调，在这个语境中
but also I want to emphasize that in these contexts
“好”是一个相对的词
and good is a relative term
取决于你的期望
that depends on your expectation
建立一个解决你自己问题的工具是完全ok的
it's totally okay to build a tool that solves your own problem
然后就此结束
and call it a day
它是一个很好的工具，因为它对你有效
it's a great tool that works for you anyway
实际上
and actually
我有很多这样的工具，我对它们很满意
I have plenty of such tools and I'm happy about that
即使没有其他人使用它们
even though no one else is going to use them
但它们让我在一天结束时完成了工作
but they got me job done at the end of day right
所以让我们重新审视我们的目标
so let's revise our goal
假设我们想要建立一个工具，可以
let's say we want to build a tool that can
不仅对我们自己有用，还能对更多人有帮助
be beneficial not only ourselves but also more people
并且社区也可以帮助我们改进
and probably the community could also help us back
使工具能够帮助到更多的人
and make the tools better for everyone
所以问题变成了我们如何
so the question becomes how
可以制作一个
could we make a
通用且有用的工具供人们使用
general and useful tool for people to use
我会说每个决定都伴随着权衡
well I'd say that every decision comes
当用户考虑是否要使用工具时
with a tradeoff and when users consider if they want to use a tool
他们会证明你可以从中获得的成本和收益是合理的
they would justify the cost and benefit you could get from it so
这里有个天平
here we have a balance and we're going to
如果我要放两个最重要的
if I'm going to put two most
到天平上
important factor on the balance
那我会选择学习和使用工具成本
and I'd pick the cause of learning and using the tool
对比我实际不用工具做事情的成本
vs the cause of doing something oneself
所以为了让
so in order to make
用户愿意使用我们的工具
users willing to use our tool
我会说
I'd say that
学习成本应该远低于
the cost of learning should be much less than
实际操作的成本
the cost of doing
这一直是我的小公式
and this has been my little
用来预评估我的想法
go to formula to pre evaluate the idea I have
是否值得去做
if the idea is worthwhile or not
例如
so for example
假设我想
let's say if I want to
求10个数字的和
get a summary of 10 numbers
你会寻找
would you look
一个库来完成这件事吗
for a library to do that
可能不会
and probably no
因为我们可以用一个简单的循环
because we can do it with a single loop
两行代码来完成
of two lines of code
我们自己做的成本
and the cost of doing ourselves
太低了，我们根本不会考虑
is too low that we don't even consider
去寻找或使用工具
to searching or getting a tool
如果我们要做一些微积分
but if we are going to do some calculus
我肯定会找一个库
and I'm certainly going to find a library
来替我完成，因为我基本上忘记了
to do it for me because I basically forgot
所有我在大学学到的东西
everything I got in my college
然而另一方面
so however on the other hand
如果我们选择的库需要我们理解比如说
if the library we pick requires us to understand like
100种不同的配置
100 different configurations before
我们才能使用它
we are able to use it
我们可能不会使用它
we probably not going to
而是会寻找另一个可能更容易的库
use it and find another library that might be easier
因此我们知道
thus we know that
在制作工具时
when making tools
我们必须考虑
we have to think
这些情况，并找到一个好的平衡点
about those cases and find a good balance
使这个工具值得使用
to make the tool worthwhile
因此我们知道我们应该
so here we know that we should
尽可能降低使用这个工具的成本
probably reduce the cost of using the tool
以便让人们更容易上手
to make it easier for people to pick up
所以在我看来
so from my point of view
工具的成本由以下因素组成
the cost of the tool is composed by the following factors
第一个是发现的成本
the first one is the cost of discovering
这是关于人们通常
uh it's about how commonly people need
需要意识到他们需要一个工具
to realize they need a tool
在特定场景下
for certain text
这意味着工具应该创建时就被定义清楚
and it means that the tool should also be well defined
能用一两句话就能描述清楚，工具的具体用途
and so that people can easily get what a tool is for with one or two sentence in the description
然后就是学习成本
then we have the cost of learning
这是我认为特别重要的一点
ah this is a particularly important one in my opinion
这是关于人们多容易理解并开始使用这个工具
is that ah is how easy for people to understand and to get start with a tool
作为一个工具应该是
as a tool is supposed to be
使实际工作更容易
to be used to make the actual work easier
我们也不希望用户在使用之前花过多的时间去学习。
we certainly don't want the user to struggle on learning for a long time before they can actually get benefit from using the tool
然后是代价
and then we have the price
工具本身的成本
the cost of the tool itself
我们很幸运在开源项目中
and we're lucky that in open source
大多数工具都是免费使用的
the majority of the tools are free to use
感谢每一个在幕后的维护者和贡献者
so thanks to every maintainers and contributors behind the scene and
创造了如此多的优秀工具供大家使用
make so much awesome tools that for everyone to use
但是当然，另一方面
but of course like on the other hand
如果工具不是免费的
if the tool is not free this definitely go into
这肯定会成为用户选择工具时考虑的一个因素
one of the factors that user would consider on choosing
最后一个是采用的成本
and then the last one is the cost of adoption
比如如何将一个工具集成或安装到项目中
like how to integrate or how to install one tool into one project
以及工具对未来需求的扩展性
and how extendable the tool is for potential future needs
以及迁移的成本是多少等等
and how much migration would cost stc
所有这些因素实际上是由于
so all those factors
使用外部工具而引入的
are actually introduced because the use of an external tool
最后
um in the end
我们希望工具的成本能被它提供的好处所抵消
we want the cost of the tool being paid off by the benefit it provides
因此我们知道事物存在复杂性
so we know that's the complexity of things
可能会从一个地方转移到另一个地方
might transfer from one place to the other
但不会神奇地消失
but not going to magically disappear
所以如果我们要解决一个复杂的问题
so if we are going to solve a complex problem
也很难避免工具变得复杂
it's really kind of hard to prevent a tool from getting complex too
所以对于此
so for that
我从流行的开源项目中学到的是
what I learned from the popular open source projects
有一种叫做渐进式的东西
out there is something called progressive
因此在这个长篇介绍之后，我们终于回到我们的
so after this long intro we finally get back to our
今天的话题，什么是渐进式
topic today, what is progressive
我认为渐进式本身是相当于自我扩展
I think progressive itself is pretty self-expanding
这里我们用插图来举个例子
here let's take a quick example with illustrations
所以，这是我
so yeah, this is me
我试图从一楼
and I'm trying to get from the first floor
到二楼
to the second floor
但不幸的是，我撞到了墙
but unfortunately I hit a wall
唯一的办法就是跳过这堵墙
the only way to get there is to jump through the wall
但我不是一个很有运动细胞的人
but I'm not a very sports person
所以我跳不过去
so I'm not able to jump that high
可能我会放弃然后掉头走回去
in that case, I might give up and turn back
这很遗憾，因为
this is a shame because
我没有实现我想要的目标
I kind of fail to accomplish what I'm aiming for
因为这太难了
because this is too hard
但从渐进式的角度来看
but from a progressive perspective
我认为这就是为什么发明了楼梯
I think that's why stairs were invented
它允许我们逐步向上走，最终实现一个目标
it allows us to take multiple small steps and go upward, and eventually achieve a goal
如果没有则很难实现
that would be very hard to achieve without it
所以在这里
so here
我对渐进的理解是楼梯
my interpretation of progressive is that stairs
使事情更容易接近
make things easier to approach
所以让我们来
so let's take
一些实际工作中的例子，比如渐进式在日常工具中的应用
some real work examples, like how progressive works in our daily tools
如果你去 Vue 的官方网站
so if you go to Vue's official documentation
vuejs.org，你会看到标题
vuejs.org, you will see the headline
将其描述为一个渐进式 JavaScript 框架
describes it as a progressive JavaScript framework
在文档中有一个声明提到
and inside the docs, there is a statement mentioning that
Vue 是一个可以随着你成长和需求而变化的框架
Vue is a framework that can grow with you and adapt to your needs
我听人说过
I have heard people say that
Vue 的一个主要卖点是它非常容易学习和上手
one of the main selling points of Vue is that it is very easy to learn and get started
更重要的是，我看到
and more than that, I see that
Vue 很棒，因为它几乎可以在任何地方使用
Vue is awesome because it can be used basically everywhere
感谢它所采用的渐进式理念
thanks to the progressive approach it takes
Vue 在集成方面是渐进式的
so Vue is progressive in terms of integration
Vue 提供了很多中使用方式
Vue provides multiple views and offers many ways
以便在不同的场景中使用
for it to be used in different scenarios
比如你可以使用 Vue
like you can use Vue in a
以单行 CDN 导入
single line of CDN import
就可以在你的 Web应用中使用
to enhance your web applications
即使是在没有任何构建工具的静态 HTML 文件中
even in a static HTML file without any build tool
然后我们也可以将 Vue 组件用作 Web components
and then we can also use Vue components as web components
所以它可以与其他框架共存
so it can coexist with other frameworks
反之亦然
vice versa
你也可以在你的 Vue 应用中导入 Web component
you can also import web components in your Vue applications
当我们有了 Vue 构建工具后
and when we have the Vue tool setup
我们可以使用 Vite 创建 Vue 应用
we can build Vue applications with
例如
Vite, for example
使用 Vue 的单文件组件
with Vue single file components
将必要的上下文放在一个文件中
and colocate necessary contexts inside a single file
这让我们能够轻松地构建
this allows us to build
交互式的单页应用程序
interactive single-page applications with ease
使用像 VitePress 这样的工具，它允许你
and with tools like VitePress, it allows you to
高效地进行静态站点生成
efficiently generate static sites
并且仅加载最少的 JavaScript
that ship minimal JavaScript
同时保持良好的开发者体验
while maintaining a great developer experience
使用像 Nuxt 这样的工具，我们可以使用 Vue 进行服务器端渲染
and with tools like Nuxt, we could have server-side rendering with Vue
以最大化用户体验
to maximize the user experience
和更好的 SEO 结果
and as well as the better SEO result
本地也可以通过 Ionic 或
native targeting is also possible by Ionic or
NativeScript 来实现
NativeScript
正如 Jessica 刚才做了一个很棒的展示
as Jessica just made an awesome showcase
然后我们有
and then we have the
即将到来的 Vapor 模式，它允许组件
upcoming Vapor mode, which allows components
选择更高性能的无虚拟 DOM 渲染引擎
to opt in a more performant, virtual DOM-less render engine
以进一步优化一些场景的性能表现
to optimize even further for performance-critical scenarios
因此，Vue 的方法在集成层面上是渐进式的
so Vue's approach provides progressiveness on the level of integrations
这使得它能覆盖不同场景的需求
it allows it to cover the needs for different scenarios
甚至与其他技术共存
or even coexist with other technologies
这意味着即使你有一个大的
this means even if you have a large
代码库使用了其他技术栈
codebase with another stack
但是你也想开始使用 Vue
but you also want to get started with using Vue
你可以先在应用程序的一部分使用 Vue
you can adopt some part of your app using Vue first
然后逐步迁移每个部分
and gradually migrate each part slowly
据我所知
and as far as I know
比如像 WikiMedia 也
like for example, WikiMedia also
选择了 Vue 作为
picked Vue as their
下一代框架并开始切换
next framework and started to enhance it with Vue
最后
in the end
我们的目标是让我们的工具
the goal is to make our tool
易于适应不同的场景
easy to adopt for different scenarios
和需求，以便我们能够
and needs so that we can
服务于广泛的用户
serve a wide range of users
然后我们来说一下Nuxt
and then let's talk about Nuxt
战术喝水
如果你访问 nuxt.com
if you go to nuxt.com
你会看到它被称为
you will see it's been titled as
直观的 Vue 框架
the Intuitive Vue Framework
在文档中提到
and in the docs, it mentions
Nuxt 的目标是让 Web
Nuxt's goal is to make the web
直观且高性能
intuitive and performant
并提供出色的开发者体验
with a great developer experience
这引出了下一节内容
and that brings us to the next section
渐进式引导
progressive on onboarding
如果你尝试过 Nuxt 的启动模板
if you have ever tried Nuxt's starter template
你会发现开始一个 Nuxt 应用程序非常容易
you will find it's surprisingly easy to start a Nuxt app
你所需要做的就是
if um all you need to do
将 Nuxt 安装为你的开发依赖项
is to have Nuxt installed as your dev dependency
并创建一个简单的 Vue 文件组件
and create a simple Vue file component
呃，作为 Vue 文件
uh, as a Vue file
就是这样
and that's it
这就是你开始使用 Nuxt 所需的一切
that's all you need to get started with Nuxt
即使对于从未尝试过 Nuxt 或 Vue 的人来说
even for someone who has never tried Nuxt or Vue
也不难看出它会渲染什么
it's probably not hard to tell what it will render
或者如何修改变成你想要的样子
or how to modify it to change the text you want
只要他们对 HTML 有基本的了解
as long as they have a basic idea of what HTML is
所以我认为 Nuxt 的直观性在于
so I think Nuxt's intuitiveness here
你可以用非常少的知识就能使用它
means that you can get started with very minimal knowledge
而且它也应该相当容易
while it should also be fairly easy
在需要时启用更多功能
to enable more features as you need them
所以让我们谈谈 Nuxt 的另一个方面
so let's talk about the other aspect of Nuxt
Nuxt擅长的部分
what Nuxt is good at
渐进式特性
progressive on features
我们知道 Nuxt 是
so we know that Nuxt was
以最小的形式启动
with a bare minimum status
但我们也知道在现实世界中
but we also know that in a real world
应用程序不会看起来那么简单
application that it won't be looked that simple
所以我们需要很多功能来满足各种需求
so we need a lot of capabilities to accomplish various needs
同时
and also
我们需要一种方法来以可管理的方式组织代码
a way for us to organize the code in a manageable way
所以 Nuxt 是一个可以随着你需求增长的框架
so Nuxt is a framework that can grow with you
呃，随着你的需求
uh, with your needs
比如说呃，如果
like to say um, if
如果你想要一些组件来分离
if you want some components to be separate
并重用逻辑
and reuse logic
在 Nuxt 中你可以
in Nuxt, you can
你只需在compnents/ 文件夹下创建 组件文件
you can just create the components files under the components directory
它们会自动
and they will be auto
在你的项目中被发现
discoverable across your project
然后如果我们的
and then if our
应用程序需要服务多个页面和导航
app needs the capability of serving multiple pages and navigations
你可以创建一个pages/文件夹
you can create a pages directory and
它将为你设置 Vue 路由器
it will set up the Vue router for you and the components
该目录下的组件将根据文件名自动注册到你的路由中
under the directory will be automatically registered to your route based on their file name
另一个很棒的部分是，你虽然这么做了
other great parts is that until you do this
但Vue 路由器和相关代码
uh, Vue router and related code
并不需要写到你的应用程序中
shipped to your production app before you actually use them
假设我们的应用程序现在已经准备好了
say our app is now ready to go
我们想把网站部署到某个地方
and we want to deploy the site somewhere
有很多部署平台可以选择
there are quite many deploy platforms that you can choose from
所以通常你需要学习一些
so usually you need to
比如如何在某平台上部署某框架
learn a little bit like how to deploy X framework on the Y platform, etc.
但是使用 Nuxt
but with Nuxt
它几乎可以不需要配置就可以启动api服务
it just works on all major hosting services with zero configuration
感谢由 Nitro 提供的自动部署功能
thanks to the automatic deploy presets powered by Nitro
这对于一个 Web 应用程序来说也很常见
it's also common for a web app
有一些服务器逻辑
to have some server logic
和 API 接口
and API endpoints
在 Nuxt 中你可以简单地创建一个
in Nuxt, you can simply create a
server/api 的目录
server/api directory
使用与页面路由类似的约定
with a very similar convention to pages for routing
Nitro 会将它们部署到无服务器函数
Nitro will deploy them to a serverless function
基于托管服务
based on the hosting service
并且在开发过程中具有端到端类型安全
and will have end-to-end type safety on development
说到类型安全，如果你后来
so talking about type safety, if later
学习 JavaScript 并想在 Nuxt 中使用它
you learn JavaScript and want to use it in Nuxt
没问题，它会正常工作
no problem, it will just work
因为 Nuxt 已经可以解析它了
and as Nuxt is already understanding it
例如更多功能如渐进式 Web 应用（PWA）
like for more features like progressive web apps
搜索引擎优化（SEO），国际化（i18n）等
search engine optimizations, internationalization etc
Nuxt 提供了模块生态系统，可以与它们集成
Nuxt provides a richmodule ecosystem that can integrate with them
只需简单的引入
with a few clicks
最后，如果
and finally, in case
你对更多功能感兴趣，Nuxt 还提供一个 Nuxt devtools工具
you are interested in more features, Nuxt also provides a Nuxt devtools
供你检查内部和分析的工具
for you to inspect internals or analyze your tools
所有这些功能都是可选的
all these features are opt-in
这意味着如果你不需要某个功能
meaning that if you don't need a certain feature
你根本不需要学习它
you don't need to learn it at all
一旦你觉得它有用
and once you find it useful later
你可以轻松地重新获取它
you can always grab it back easily
为了帮助这些优秀的功能被发现
to help with feature discovery
我们制作了 Nuxt devtools
we made the Nuxt devtools
就像我之前提到的
as we just mentioned
例如，Nuxt devtools 提供了一个模块选项卡
for example, the Nuxt devtools provides a modules tab
你可以快速概览
that you can have a quick overview
你安装了多少模块
of how many modules you have installed
并且有链接到它们的文档或源码仓库
and with a link to their documentation or source code repo
还有一个很好的 UI 界面
and it also offers you a nice UI
你可以在社区中寻找所有模块
for you to search through all the modules across the community
你可以让 devtool 自动下载并安装它们
and you can ask devtool to automatically download and install them
只需在 UI 界面中单击一下
with a single click inside the UI
所以 devtool 是为帮助用户发现和理解功能模块
so devtool is built to help feature discovery and understanding
并帮助你
and to assist you
拥有更棒的应用程序
to have an even more awesome application
顺便说一下，我们已经看到
yeah, just by the way, we already saw
这里有很多devtools插件
the the devtool kit tag made by Gyome so
我们希望这些功能能给用户带来更多框架上的选择
we hope that these features can be brought to more the other framework
在文档网站之上 Nuxt 已经
and on top of documentation sites, Nuxt has
在过去的几个月里，我们开始
in the past few months, we started
构建一个交互式教程
to build an interactive tutorial playground
一些人可能已经看过相关的直播
some of you probably have watched a live streaming on building it
顺便一提，感谢当时参与看直播和我一起完成工作的大家
thank you for working together with me, by the way
所以 Nuxt 教程允许初学者有一个更线性的
so Nuxt Tutorial allows beginners to have a more linear
一步一步的学习体验
step-by-step learning experience
这样他们可以更容易地开始使用 Nuxt
so they can start playing with Nuxt more easily
即使不需要设置或安装 Nuxt
even without the need to set up or install Nuxt
这是我们尝试获得的另一个案例
it's just another case that we are trying to get
更顺畅的渐进式引导体验
the progressive onboarding experience even smoother
简而言之，我们的观点是我们应该
so in short, the point here is that we should
随着用户成长，而不是一下子
grow with users and not putting too much things
同时提供太多东西
up front at once
使事情变得更容易起步，并逐步引入新的概念和功能
making things easier to start with and expose new concepts and powers progressively along the way
然后让我们谈谈另一个例子 Vite
then let's talk about one more example, Vite
Vite 目标是下一代前端工具
Vite titles itself as the next generation frontend tooling
我相信没有人会质疑这一点
I'm pretty sure no one would question that
Vite 的理念中提到
in Vite philosophy's action, the docs mention
“Vite会与生态系统紧密合作，以尽量减少发布自身功能”
Vite works closely with projects in the ecosystem to minimize the regressions on each release
让我们看看它是如何做的
and let's see how it's done in action
Vite 现在是第 5 个主要版本
and Vite is on major version 5 right now
在过去的 4 年里，我们基本上
and during the past 4 years, we basically
保持这种节奏，比如
keep the pace, it's like
每年发布一个主要版本
releasing one major version per year
去同步 JavaScript 生态系统和标准的不断演变
to keep the JavaScript ecosystem and evolving standards
有些人可能
some of you probably
经历过那个时期
have been through that period
我们确实进行了重大发布
we do major releases
最后一个 V5 是去年（2023年）十一月发布的
the last one, V5, was released in November last year (2023)
所以并不是很远
so not too far away
众所周知，Vite的版本发布有一个非常顺利的迁移路径
and it's not a secret that vite major releases have a very smooth migration path
我们收到很多评论提到
and we receive many comments mentioning that
他们成功的迁移案例
their successful migration cases
Moonrapo 提到他们升级 Vite
so Project Moonrapo mentioned they upgraded
V2 到 V3 仅仅通过版本升级
V2 to V3 with only bumping the version
所有功能都正常运转
and everything keeps working as is
Kilian 甚至将 Vite 描述为生态中版本升级最无痛的工具
so Kilian even described Vite as the most painless version upgrades in a beauty ecosystem ever
在 Vite 5发布的时候
on the release of Vite5
有很多类似的评论
so many comments like this
感谢你们，我们很高兴听到这些评论
and thank you, we are glad to hear those stories
所以如果你观察你正在使用的 Vite 插件
so if you look into Vite plugins of you are using
你会发现他们中的许多
you will find many of
遵循类似这张图的模式
their packaged follow a similar pattern like this
vite 出现在
and vite appears in the
预依赖关系中，并且版本范围从 V5
pre dependency and with the version range from V5
一直到 V2
all the way down to V2
这意味着插件可以从 V2 到 V5 完美运行
this means that plugins keep working from V2 to V5 perfectly
无需放弃对之前Vite 版本的支持
without the need to drop the support for the previous Vite version
更不用说这中间相隔了三年
not to mention that there is 3 years in between
对于像 Vite 这样活跃的工具来说
for such active tools like Vite
Vite 投入了大量的心力来实现这一点
Vite has put a lot of cares to make this possible
我们非常关心
and we care a lot
我们做的每一个改变
on every change we made
我们甚至提出了生态系统 CI 的理念
and we even work out the idea of ecosystem CI that
在每个节点上跑主流下游框架的测试
runs the test of the major downstream frameworks on almost every progress
以确保对生态系统的影响最小
to make sure they have minimal impact to the ecosystem
这个实践后来被 Vue、Nuxt 和许多其他框架采纳
practice has later been adopted to Vue, Nuxt and many other frameworks
让我们再来谈谈渐进式破坏性更新
so let's talk about progressive on breaking changes
我猜大概没有人喜欢破坏性更新
I guess probably no one likes breaking changes
但一些情况下破坏性更新在某种程度上也很重要
but somehow breaking changes are also quite important
比如保持代码库的健康
for the codebases to stay healthy
比如长期内更易于维护
and more maintainable in the long run
它帮助我们修复
it helps us to fix
我们之前设计中的不完美之处
the imperfections in our previous design
利用现有更好的生态
with the better context we have today
虽然很难避免引入它们
while it's hard to avoid introducing them
我相信有些方法可以让过渡更顺利和让用户更容易接受
I believe there make the transition smoother and easier for users to adopt
所以结合我们在 Vue 和 Vite 中的经验
So taking the experience we had in Vue and Vite
我认为有两种主要方法可以实现这一点
I see there are two major ways to achieve that
所以我们回到之前的图表
So we bring back the graph we had before
关于从第一个大版本到第二个大版本的跳跃
Referring the jump between major version 1 to 2, for example
一个使破坏性变更渐进式的方法是向前兼容
And one way to make breaking changes progressively is to do forward compatibility
另一个方法是向后兼容，我来解释下
And the other is backward compatibility. Let me explain
前向兼容是
Forward compatibility is
指与未来版本兼容
About being compatible with versions in the future
例如，如果你知道
Like to say if you know
你将会有一个新特性
You're going to have a new feature
会放在下一个破坏性变更中
And in the next breaking change
你可以在当前版本中引入这个特性
You can bring the feature back in the current version
以非破坏性的方式
In a non-breaking way
在实践中，我们经常引入
In practice, we often introduce
实验或特性的标志
Flags like experimental or features
用插件的方式集成，用户就可以在当前版本中开启并使用它们
For users to explicitly opt in changes  if they want to try new stuff mentioning of the user can still be on the current version
而不破坏现有功能
without breakage
在 Vue，vue2 中有 @vue/composition-api 插件的例子
In Vue, we have the example of Vue Composition API plugin in vue2
它提供了在 Vue 2 应用中
It provides the capability of using
使用 Vue 3 组合 API 的能力
Vue 3's Composition APIs for Vue 2 apps
在迁移到 Vue 3 之前
Before they can migrate to Vue 3
然后2年后我们有了vue2.7
And later we have Vue 2.7  two years after
在 Vue 3.0 发布两年后
Two years after Vue 3.0 has been released
为了支持组合 API
To have the Composition API support
更多地与 Vue 3 的行为和功能集对齐
Aligning more with Vue 3's behavior and feature set
在 Nuxt 中，我们引入了
In Nuxt, we introduced
Nuxt Bridge 以连接 Nuxt 2 和 3 之间的变更
Nuxt Bridge to bridge the changes between Nuxt 2 and 3
让我们谈谈向后兼容
And let's talk about backward compatibility
你可能更常听到
Which you probably heard more often
这意味着与之前版本兼容
This is about compatibility with the previous version
一种常见的做法是
A common practice is that
我们会将某个功能标记为已弃用
We will mark a certain feature as deprecated
并在使用时打印警告
And print warnings upon usage
并最终在后续的major版本中移除
And eventually remove it in the later major version
所以这意味着
So that means that
最好进行小版本的发布而不是频繁更新主版本
It's better to do smaller but also more frequent major releases
以使迁移更容易
To make the migration easier
谈到例子
Taking about examples
Vue 3 有兼容性构建，我们有 @vue/compat
Vue 3 has the compatibility build，we have @vue/compat
它建立在 Vue 3 的基础上
Which is built on top of the foundation of Vue 3
额外添加了标志来模拟
With additional flags to simulate
Vue 2 的旧行为
The legacy Vue 2 behavior
你可以在迁移时使用它
That you can use during the migration
在 Nuxt 中，我们有 @nuxt/kit
In Nuxt, we have @nuxt/kit
允许模块作者编写可在 Nuxt 2 和 3 中都可以使用的模块，等等
That allows module authors to build modules that can work in both Nuxt 2 and Nuxt 3 etc
所以从我的，从我的
so from my under uh from my
从我的理解呃
from my understanding uh
我认为渐进式破坏性变更
I think progressive of breaking change
是从根本上
is fundamentally
允许共存
allow of the coexistence
当我们做变更时
when when we make changes
我们应该提供一个“中间阶段”让人们开始
we should provide the middle stage for people to start
进行迁移
uh to take a rest on migration
允许在旧的和新的共存
um allowing to coexist on both legacy and new
这样工作可以渐进地进行
so the work can be done progressively
并减少破坏性改动
and reduce the chance of uh breakage
总结今天的话题
so to recap today's topic
我们讨论了制作工具中的不同方面的渐进式理论
we talk about progressive on different aspects of building tools
首先是关于渐进式引导
the first is about progressive on boarding
我们应该使工具易于
and we should make a tool easy to
学习和理解
learn and understand
让更多的人可以开始使用我们开发的工具
for more people to get started with the tool we're going to build
然后我们谈论了渐进式集成
and then we talk about progressive on integrations
让工具可以涵盖
for tools to cover
不同的场景并易于去使用
a different scenario and easier to adopt
然后我们有渐进式特性
then we have the progressive on features
我们通常希望我们的工具
it's pretty common that we want
功能强大
our tool to be powerful
但也可能让用户感到难以入手
but also can be overwhelming to users to start with
所以采取渐进式方法可以让我们
so taking the progressive approach would
从最小实现开始，随着用户的需求而增长并最终满足用户需求
allow us to start with minimum and grow with the user as user needs
最后我们有渐进式破坏性更新
and finally we have progressive braking changes
提供“中间阶段”以使项目更容易逐步迁移
to provide the middle stage to make migration easier step by step
还有许多其他方面的渐进式理论
so there are many much more aspect of progressiveness that
我们今天没有时间谈论
we don't have time to talk about this today
但我的目标是向你们提出渐进之路的想法
but my goal here is to bring up the idea of progressive paths to you
这可能看起来并不是一种会让人感到兴奋的很酷或特别的事情
it might not seem to be a very cool unusual things that people would get excited about
但我认为这个理论可以在我们日常开发中扮演着重要的角色
but I think this plays a very important role to our daily software development
同时我认为它不仅可以在我们开发工具中
and we should think about it more often when we're building stuff
不仅仅在开源项目中，同时也可以
not only for open source project but it can also
用在我们的产品中
be used for your products
或者在我们日常开发的工具中
or the way of doing stuff in general
用一句话来结束我今天的演讲
so to finish my talk in one sentence I'd say
提供渐进之路是为了让用户能够通过分而治之的方式
to provide the progressive path is to enable users capability of divide and conquers
去实现他们的目标
towards the goal they have
我希望你们喜欢并觉得有用
and I hope you enjoy and find it useful
这就是我今天演讲的全部内容
and that's all for my talk
谢谢大家，祝 happy hacking
thank you and happy hacking